Register to the Charles Wesley Ervin collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Wesley Ervin collection
1927-1973
97049
Ervin, Charles Wesley, collector.
3 manuscript boxes, 1 microfilm box (1.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Internal bulletins, minutes, other internal documents, pamphlets, and serial issues, issued by Trotskyist organizations in India, Sri Lanka, the United States and elsewhere, and by the International Secretariat for the Fourth International, relating to international Trotskyism. Includes some minutes of the Workers (Communist) Party of the United States.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired the collection form Charles Wesley Ervin in 1997, with subsequent increments following.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Charles Wesley Ervin Collection consists of internal documents and publications of Trotskyist and Trotskyist-related organizations. It is especially strong in issuances of Trotskyist organizations in India and to a lesser extent Sri Lanka, and was used as research material for the book by Charles Wesley Ervin, Tomorrow Is Ours: Trotskyism in India and Ceylon, 1935-48 (Colombo, 2006). The collection also contains rare issuances from Trotskyist groups in the United States, especially early splinter groups from the Socialist Workers Party and its predecessors. There are also minutes and other internal documents of the Workers (Communist) Party from 1927-1928, just before the party's expulsion of the pioneering American Trotskyists. Completing the collection are rare issuances from the 1930s of the international movement for the Fourth International and single items from British and German Trotskyist groups of this period.
The collection is arranged as a single series by country of issuing organization. Issuances of the international organization of the Fourth International movement precede those of national parties.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Communism.; Communism--United States.; Communism--Great Britain.; Communism--Germany.; Fourth International.; Communist Party of the United States of America.
Collection Contents
- Movement for the Fourth International issuances (Folder 1)
  - Bulletin intérieur international (International Secretariat for the Fourth International). No. 1-3 (1937 April-1938 early May) (Folder 1: 1)
  - Bulletin international (International Youth Secretariat for the Fourth International). Unnumbered (1937 November 10), no. 3 (1938 February) (Folder 1: 2)
  - Circulaire (International Secretariat for the Fourth International). No. 1 (1938 April 1) (Folder 1: 3)
  - Service d'information et de presse (International Secretariat for the Fourth International). No. 8-11 (1936 September 13-October 2), no. 13-21/22 (1936 November 4-1937 early August) (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Report of Conference on Sections for the Fourth International" (report by British delegate to the conference), 1936 (Folder 1: 5)
- Germany. Mitteilungsblatt der I.K.D. (Internationale Kommunisten Deutschlands). No. 3 (1938 September) (Folder 1: 6)
- Great Britain. National Bulletin (National Conference of the Bolshevik-Leninist Organisations in Britain). 1938 (Folder 1: 7)
- India (Folder 1)
  - Marxist Outlook (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 1)
    - 1966. Vol. 1 no. 1-5 (February-May) (Folder 1: 8)
    - 1966. Vol. 1 no. 6-11 (June-December) (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1967. Vol. 1 no. 12 (January), vol. 2 no. 1-10 (February-November) (Folder 1: 10)
    - 1968. Vol. 2 no. 11/12 (January or February [conflicting dates]), vol. 3 no. 1 (March), vol. 3 no. 5/7 (October) (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1970. Vol. 5 no. 1-7 (February-August) (Folder 1: 12)
  - Red Spark (Socialist Workers Party/Communist League of India) (Folder 1)
    - 1970. Vol. 1 no. 1 (December) (Folder 1: 13)
    - 1971. Vol. 2 no. 1 (March), vol. 2 no. 3/5 (November) (Folder 2: 1)
    - 1972. Vol. 3 no. 1/2 (February), vol. 3 no. 5/6-7/9 (June-October) (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1973. Vol. 4 no. 3/6 (August), vol. 4 no. 9/12 (December) (Folder 2: 3)
- Pamphlets (Folder 2)
  - Communist League of India and Bangla Desh., 1972 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Draft Policy Statement(All-India Mazdoor Kisan Party)., 1955 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Election Manifesto of the Socialist Workers Party., 1970 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Hutheesing, Sarojini. The Tibetan Struggle (Revolutionary Communist Party of India). Undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - In Defence of Socialism: Why We Condemn the "Merger" with the Praja Party (Socialist Party)., 1952 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Mishra, Anand (Folder 2)
    - East European Crisis of Stalinism: Berlin, Poznan, Hungary (Communist League)., 1957 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Stalinism: What It Means: A Critical Appraisal of the 20th Congress of the C.P.S.U., 1956 (Folder 2: 10)
    - The Programme for a Socialist Revolution in India (Socialist Workers Party)., 1968 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Programme of the Communist League., 1954 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Roy, Lily. Socialism Reaffirmed: A Reply to Mr. Masani., 1944 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Sen, Indra. Communist Policy Today: A Marxist Analysis., 1952 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Shukla, Chandravadan. Socialistic Pattern?, 1955 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Tagore, Saumyendranath (Folder 2)
    - Bourgeois-Democratic Revolution and India. 1939 (reprint 1946) (Folder 2: 16)
    - Congress-Socialism. Bengali edition 1936 (2nd English edition 1946) (Folder 2: 17)
    - The Hour Has Struck., 1949 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Leftism and Leftist Unity., 1946 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Permanent Revolution. 1944 (2nd edition 1948) (Folder 2: 20)
    - Stalin, Truman: Hands Off Korea., 1951 (Folder 2: 21)
    - Tactics and Strategy of Revolution., 1948 (Folder 2: 22)
    - The Treacherous Marsh., 1948 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Leaflet. "Open Letter to All Congress Socialists by Mazdoor Trotskyist Party of India." Undated (Folder 2: 24)
  - Indian languages material (Folder 2)
    - Vishwa Kranti. No. 1-8 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Four pamphlets (Folder 2: 26)
    - Leaflets (Folder 2: 27)
  - Typescript English translations of passages from publications in Indian languages, 1939-1952 (Folder 2: 28)
- Microfilm (Folder 3)
  - Reel 1. For a Workers' and Peasants' Government in India (Revolutionary Workers Party of India), 1958; Bolshevik-Leninist-Trotskyist Draft Provisional Programme, undated; Draft Programme (Mazdoor Trotskyist Party of India), 1942; Socialist Workingmen's Fortnightly, 1948 April 25-August 1; New Spark, 1952 November 7; Militant (Revolutionary Workers Party of India), 1959 April 5-1961 January; New Spark (Bolshevik-Leninist Party of India), 1948 January 3-September 4; Indian languages material; New Spark, 1947 April 26-December 20 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Reel 2. Spark, 1946 early March-late July (not in order); Permanent Revolution, 1943 July/September; C. R. Govindan, First Round of European Socialist Revolution, 1945 (Folder 3: 2)
- Sri Lanka. Pamphlets by Colvin R. de Silva (Folder 4)
  - Left Disunity: A Reply to a Critic., 1950 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Outline of the Permanent Revolution: A Study Course (Lanka Samasamaja Party). 1955 (Folder 4: 2)
  - The Present Political Situation in India (Bolshevik-Leninist Party parliamentary fraction, Ceylon)., 1948 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Their Politics--And Ours (Lanka Samasamaja Party)., 1954 (Folder 4: 4)
- United States (Folder 4)
  - Communist League of Struggle (Albert Weisbord group). The Struggle for Communism: The Position of the Internationalist-Communists of the United States., 1935 (Folder 4: 5)
  - International Workers School (New York; Communist League of America). "Organization Principles" course outline., Undated (1930s) (Folder 4: 6)
  - Marx-Lenin School (Chicago; Communist League of America). "Imperialism and the Proletarian Revolution" course outline (Albert Glotzer, instructor)., Undated (1930s) (Folder 4: 7)
  - Revolutionary Workers League (Hugo Oehler group; includes predecessor caucus within Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 4)
    - International News. Unnumbered (1935) (Folder 4: 8)
    - Internal Bulletin. No. 3 (1935) (Folder 4: 9)
  - Minutes, 1935 October 3-1936 January 28 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Internal documents. Resolutions and circular letters, 1935-1936 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Leaflets, 1935-1936 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Socialist Union of America (Bert Cochran/George Clarke group). The Educator. Vol. 1 no. 1-7 (1953 December-1954 December), vol. 2 no. 1 (1955 October), vol. 3 no. 1 (1956 June) (Folder 4: 13)
  - Spartacus Youth League (Workers Party of the United States). International Bulletin vol. 1 no. 6/vol. 2 no. 1 (1934 December/1935 January); Organizational Bulletin (1935 January); Educational Bulletin on the Paris Commune (1935 March) (Folder 4: 14)
  - Workers (Communist) Party. Political Committee minutes, 1927 March 22-August 12; internal documents, including resolutions, motions and circular letters, 1927-1928 (Folder 4: 15)